John J. Sirica Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John J. Sirica Papers 1932-1986 1957-1986
MSS81883
Sirica, John J.
38,000 items
125 containers plus 1 classified
49.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Judge and lawyer. Correspondence, memoranda, drafts of articles and books, speeches, notes, research materials calendars, case files, bench books, financial and legal material, family papers, printed material, diaries, and other papers pertaining chiefly to Sirica's career as judge of the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia, especially to cases relating to the Watergate Affair.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ammidown, Robert Louis--Trials, litigation, etc.; Clark, Tom C. (Tom Campbell), 1899-1977--Correspondence.; Dempsey, Jack, 1895-1983.; Ervin, Sam J., Jr. (Sam James), 1896-1985--Correspondence.; Gimbel, Bernard F., 1885-1966--Correspondence.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972--Correspondence.; Jaworski, Leon--Correspondence.; Johnson, Frank M. (Frank Minis), 1918-1999--Correspondence.; Kronheim, Milton S. (Milton Stanley), 1911- --Correspondence.; Lear, Norman--Correspondence.; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet)--Correspondence.; McCord, James W., Jr. (James Walter), 1924-2017--Correspondence.; Neal, James F., 1929-2010--Correspondence.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994 RN: the memoirs of Richard Nixon. 1978.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994--Correspondence.; Prettyman, E. Barrett (Elijah Barrett), 1891-1971--Correspondence.; Rogers, William P. (William Pierce), 1913-2001--Correspondence.; Sinatra, Frank, 1915-1998--Correspondence.; Sirica, John J.; Sirica, John J. (John Joseph)--Correspondence.; Sirica, John J. To set the record straight: the break-in, the tapes, the conspirators, the pardon. 1979.; Wilson, John J. (John Johnston), 1901- --Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Congress. House. Select Committee to Investigate the Federal Communications Commission.; United States. District Court (District of Columbia)
Subjects
Administrative law.; Antitrust law.; Civil rights.; Constitutional law.; District courts--Washington (D.C.); Practice of law--Washington (D.C.); Trials (Murder); Watergate Affair, 1972-1974.
Occupations
Judges.; Lawyers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of John J. Sirica, lawyer and judge, were given to the Library of Congress by his wife, Lucile C. Sirica, in 1993. Additional items were purchased by the Library of Congress in 2019.
Additional Description
A description of the John J. Sirica Papers appears in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1993.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Sound and video recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division, including several tapes of the court proceedings of the Watergate case, United States v. Mitchell. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the John J. Sirica Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John J. Sirica are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of classified material in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish further information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, 19 Mar. Born, Waterbury, Conn.
1926 LL.B., Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
1926 1930 Private legal practice, Washington, D.C.
1930 1934 Assistant United States attorney for the District of Columbia, Washington, D.C.
1934 1944 Private legal practice, Washington, D.C.
1944 General counsel, Select Committee to Investigate the Federal Communications Commission, United States House of Representatives
1949 1957 Member, law firm of Hogan and Hartson, Washington, D.C.
1952 Married Lucile M. Camalier
1957 1986 Judge, United States District Court for the District of Columbia; chief judge, 1971-1974; senior judge, 1977-1986
1973 Named Time magazine's man of the year Awarded American Judges Association's award of merit
1979 Published To Set the Record Straight: The Break-in, the Tapes, the Conspirators, the Pardon (New York: W. W. Norton. 394 pp.)
1992, 14 Aug. Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John J. Sirica (1904-1992) span the years 1932-1986 with the majority of the papers concentrated between 1957 and 1986. The bulk of the papers documents Sirica's career as judge of the United States District Court for the District of Columbia, 1957-1986. The papers consist of six series: Correspondence, United States District Court File, Speeches and Writings File, Miscellany, 2021 Addition, and Classified.
The Correspondence series, 1957-1986, includes incoming and outgoing correspondence relating mostly to Sirica's personal interests and activities, although some of the letters also pertain to his professional career. Also included are a few letters from Sirica to his son, John J. Sirica, Jr.
Documenting Sirica's thirty years of service as a federal trial judge, papers in the United States District Court File, 1952-1986, comprise almost seventy-five percent of the collection. The District Court File consists of five subseries: Personal Case Calendars, Correspondence, Case File, Bench Books, and Office File. The Personal Case Calendars, 1967-1970, and Correspondence, 1968-1985, document some of the administrative functions of the court and Sirica's professional duties. The case calendars occasionally have notations about personal appointments.
The Case File subseries, 1952-1986, includes correspondence and memoranda, chiefly between Sirica and other judges, lawyers, the court clerk, and staff, as well as extensive legal material such as opinions, orders, motions, briefs, and transcripts. Papers in this subseries consist mainly of photocopies rather than original items and are organized by category into Watergate cases and other cases. Making up the bulk of the case files, the Watergate files provide extensive documentation of the court proceedings relating to the 1972 break-in at the Democratic National Committee headquarters in the Watergate apartment complex (United States v. Liddy) and the cover-up of the burglary by high ranking government officials, including the president of the United States (United States v. Mitchell). In addition, there are related cases involving the subpoena of documents and tapes from President Richard M. Nixon and the transfer of grand jury reports to the House of Representatives' Judiciary Committee (In re Grand Jury Subpoena Duces Tecum to Nixon and In re Report and Recommendation of June 5, 1972 Grand Jury Concerning Transmission of Evidence to the House of Representatives).
The remaining case files indicate the variety of cases heard by Sirica on antitrust matters, constitutional law, civil rights, government regulations, and other issues. Many of these files are incomplete and often contain only one or two items, except for two antitrust cases (electrical equipment cases and Riss & Co. v. Association of Am. R.R.) and the murder trial of Robert Louis Ammidown (United States v. Ammidown).
The final two subseries of the United States District Court File consist of Bench Books and an Office File. The Bench Book subseries, 1957-1983, contains Sirica's notes about the cases which came before his court. The Office File subseries, 1954-1986, relates to Sirica's administrative and professional duties. This subseries also documents some of the many awards and honors Sirica received throughout his career.
Papers in the Speeches and Writings File, 1949-1986, pertain mainly to Sirica's book on Watergate, To Set the Record Straight: the Break-in, the Tapes, the Conspirators, the Pardon. Also worthy of mention is a file containing the beginning pages of an autobiography.
The Miscellany series, 1932-1985, consists chiefly of material documenting Sirica's private legal practice and his service as general counsel, 1944, to the Select Committee to Investigate the Federal Communications Commission. In addition, the Miscellany series contains correspondence, 1953-1982, documenting the judge's friendship with former heavyweight boxing champion Jack Dempsey.
Among the more significant and frequent of Sirica's correspondents are Tom C. Clark, Jack Dempsey, Sam J. Ervin, Bernard F. Gimbel, J. Edgar Hoover, Leon Jaworski, Frank Minis Johnson, Milton S. Kronheim, Norman Lear, John V. Lindsay,; James W. McCord, Jr., James F. Neal, Richard M. Nixon, E. Barrett Prettyman, Jr., William P. Rogers, Frank Sinatra, and John J. Wilson.
The 2021 Addition, 1973-1978, consists of diaries kept by Sirica containing daily entries and observations, largely relating to the Watergate Affair. Also included is a copy of President Richard M. Nixon's memoir, lightly annotated by Sirica.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in six series:
Correspondence, 1957-1986
United States District Court File, 1952-1986
Speeches and Writings File, 1949-1986
Miscellany, 1932-1985
2021 Addition, 1973-1978
Classified, 1973
Container List
- Correspondence, 1957-1986 (Box 1-12)
  Correspondence and memoranda, including attachments and enclosures, between Sirica and family, friends, lawyers, judges, acquaintances, and the general public.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person or subject and therein chronologically by date.
  - Congratulatory (Box 1)
    - Judicial appointment, 1957, (9 folders)
    - Senior status, 1977-1978, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Sirica to others, 1962-1986, (2 folders)
  - Cooke, Jack Kent, 1980-1986
  - General
    - 1957, (3 folders)
    - 1958-1961, (12 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1962-1967, (10 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1968-1973, (11 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1974, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1975
      - Jan.-Sept., (4 folders)
      - Oct.-Dec. (Box 7)
    - 1976-1977, (8 folders)
    - 1978
      - Jan.-Feb.
      - Mar.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - 1979-1980, (7 folders)
    - 1981-1984, (9 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1985-1986, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Get well, selected samples
    - 1961
    - 1976
      - Feb.
        - 3-11, (3 folders)
        - 12-28, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Mar.-July, (4 folders)
      - Undated
    - 1977
    - 1984
      - Oct.
      - Nov.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 12)
      - Undated
    - 1985
- United States District Court File, 1952-1986 (Box 12-105)
  - Personal Case Calendars, 1967-1970 (Box 12)
    Calendars maintained by Sirica's staff documenting the day-to-day business of Sirica's court and his other administrative duties.
    Arranged chronologically by year.
    - 1967-1970, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1985 (Box 13-15)
    Correspondence and memoranda between Sirica and lawyers, judges, court staff, and the general public relating to his activities as a federal district judge.
    Arranged alphabetically by name of person or subject and therein chronologically.
    - Administrative (Box 13)
      - 1971-1973, (8 folders)
      - 1974 (Box 14)
    - Fund-raising, 1974-1985, (2 folders)
    - General, 1968-1981, undated, (3 folders)
    - Johnson, Frank Minis, 1973-1979
    - Postal rate case, 1975-1976, (4 folders)
    - Threatening letters, 1973-1977, (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Case File, 1952-1986 (Box 15-90)
    Correspondence, memoranda, bench books, opinions, orders, briefs, motions, transcripts, dockets, stipulations, interrogatories, reports, notes, lists, printed matter, and other legal papers pertaining to Sirica's professional activities. A systematic sample was taken of the Watergate public correspondence; fifteen percent of that correspondence was retained.
    Arranged by category into Watergate cases and other cases. The former is arranged alphabetically by type of material, and the latter alphabetically by case title.
    - Watergate cases For additional material see Container 110, To Set the Record Straight (Box 15)
      - Cases
        - In re Caddy, 1972
        - In re Grand Jury Subpoena Duces Tecum to Nixon
          - Appellate court documents, 1973, undated For additional material see Container 19, Bench Book, (3 folders)
          - General
            - 1971
            - 1973
              - Mar.-July
              - Aug.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 16)
            - 1974, undated, (3 folders)
        - In re Report & Recommendation of June 5, 1972, Grand Jury Concerning Transmission of Evidence to the House of Representatives
          - Appellate court documents, 1974
          - General, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 17)
        - In re United States Senate Select Comm. on Presidential Campaign Activities
          - 1973-1974, undated, (4 folders)
        - Mitchell v. Jaworski, 1974
        - Senate Select Comm. on Presidential Campaign Activities v. Nixon
          - 1973
            - Aug., (2 folders)
            - Sept.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 18)
            - 1974, undated
        - United States v. Liddy
          - Appellate court documents
            - 1973, (2 folders)
            - 1974
              - Jan.-Feb.
              - Mar.-Dec. (Box 19)
            - 1975-1981, undated
          - Bench book, 1972-1974
          - Docket, 1972-1977
          - General
            - 1972
              - Sept.-Oct., (2 folders)
              - Oct.-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 20)
            - 1973
              - Jan.
              - Jan.-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 21)
            - 1974-1975, undated, (3 folders) (Box 22)
          - Grand jury indictment, 1972
          - Hunt, E. Howard, motion to withdraw plea of guilt and to dismiss proceedings, 1973
          - Jury
            - Instructions, 1973
            - Selection, 1972-1973, undated
          - McCord, James W., Jr.
            - Miscellaneous motions, 1973, undated
            - New trial material, 1973-1975, undated
          - Press, 1974, undated
          - Pretrial documents, 1972
          - Sentences
            - Barker, Bernard L., Eugenio R. Martinez, Frank Sturgis, and Virgilio Gonzalez, motion to reduce, 1973-1975
            - Bureau of Prisons' reports, 1973 (Box 23)
            - Hunt, E. Howard, Jr., 1975, undated
            - Liddy, G. Gordon
              - General, 1976-1977, undated
              - Motion to reduce sentence, 1975-1977, undated, (2 folders)
            - McCord, James W., Jr., motion to reduce sentence, 1973-1975, undated
            - Presentencing file, 1973-1974, (2 folders)
            - Transcript, 1973
            - Working papers, 1973, undated
          - Transcripts
            - 1972
            - 1973
              - Jan.
                - 9-10
                - 11-22, (6 folders) (Box 24)
                - 23-30, (7 folders) (Box 25)
        - United States v. Mitchell (Box 26)
          - Appellate court documents, 1973-1978, (5 folders)
          - Bench book, 1974-1975 For additional material see Container 19, same heading
          - Bill of particulars, 1974 (Box 27)
          - Correspondence, 1973-1977, (7 folders)
          - Defendants
            - Adoption of motions of codefendants, 1974
            - Discovery, 1974
            - Motions and memoranda to dismiss the indictment, 1973-1974, (2 folders) (Box 28)
            - Publicity, 1974, (2 folders)
            - Severance, 1974
          - Disqualification of judge
            - 1974, (1 folder) (Box 29)
          - Docket, 1974-1978
          - Exhibits
            - 1A-25A (transcripts of White House tape recordings), 1972-1973 See also Container 42, White House tapes, (5 folders)
            - 26A-37A, 1973 (Box 30)
            - General, 1970-1975
            - List of exhibits and tapes played to jury, undated
          - General
            - 1972-1973, (2 folders)
            - 1974
              - Jan.-May, (2 folders)
              - May-Dec., (7 folders) (Box 31)
            - 1975-1977, (2 folders)
            - Undated (Box 32)
          - Government
            - Discovery, 1974
            - Motions and memoranda in opposition to dismiss indictment, 1974
            - Publicity, 1974
            - Severance, 1974
          - Indictment, 1974, undated, (2 folders)
          - Jury
            - Instructions
              - Final charge
                - Defendants' and government's recommendations, 1974, (2 folders)
                - General, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 33)
              - General, 1974, (2 folders)
            - Miscellaneous, 1973-1975, undated
            - Sequestration violation, alleged, 1975-1976, (2 folders)
            - Voir dire proceeding
              - General, 1974, (1 folder) (Box 34)
              - Transcripts, Oct. 1974, (6 folders) (Box 35)
          - Memoranda and briefs, 1974, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 36)
          - Motions
            - Disposition of, 1974
            - In camera inspection of Richard M. Nixon's testimony, 1975
            - Miscellaneous, 1974
          - Nixon, Richard M.
            - Subpoenas re
              - Appearance to testify, 1974-1975, (2 folders)
              - Tapes and papers (Box 37)
                - Appellate court documents, 1974, (2 folders)
                - General, 1974, (2 folders)
            - Testimony, videotape of, 1974, (2 folders)
          - Post-trial motions
            - Defendants, 1975, undated
            - Government opposition, 1975 (Box 38)
          - Pretrial
            - Conferences, 1974, (2 folders)
            - General, 1973-1974, undated, (2 folders)
            - Motions denied, 1974
          - Prosecutorial misconduct and lawyers' conspiracy, 1974
          - Sealed documents
            - Cover sheets, 1973-1974
            - General, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 39)
          - Sentences
            - Ehrlichman, John D.
              - 1974-1975, (5 folders)
              - 1976-1977 (Box 40)
            - General, 1975-1977, undated
            - Haldeman, H. R., 1975-1977, (3 folders)
            - Mardian, Robert C., 1975
            - Mitchell, John N., 1975-1978, undated, (2 folders)
          - Stipulations, 1974
          - Strachan, Gordon
            - Motion to dismiss the indictment
              - Agreement and recantation, 1974
              - General, 1974, (1 folder) (Box 41)
              - Government's opposition to, 1974
              - Immunity hearing, 1974
          - Transcripts
            - 1974
              - May-July, (2 folders)
              - July-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 42)
          - White House tapes See also Container 29, Exhibits
            - Advisory Panel on White House Tapes
              - General, 1974, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 43)
              - Report
                - Draft, 1974
                - Final, 1974
            - Correspondence, 1973-1974, (3 folders)
            - General, 1973-1974, undated, (5 folders) (Box 44)
            - Release of, 1975-1978, undated, (2 folders)
            - Transcripts
              - 1972-1973
              - 1973, (2 folders) (Box 45)
      - Correspondence
        - Professional, 1973-1978, (4 folders)
        - Public, selected samples
          - 1972
          - 1973
            - Jan.-Aug., (3 folders)
            - Sept.
              - 1-10
              - 11-28, (3 folders) (Box 46)
            - Oct.-Nov., (7 folders)
            - Dec., (2 folders) (Box 47)
            - Undated
          - 1974
            - Jan.-Apr., (6 folders)
            - May-Sept., (8 folders) (Box 48)
            - Oct.-Dec., (5 folders) (Box 49)
            - Undated
          - 1975
            - Jan.-Feb., (2 folders)
            - Mar.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 50)
          - 1976-1985, undated, (4 folders)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Anderson, Jack, disclosure of grand jury transcripts, 1973-1974
        - Baldwin, Alfred, III, unsealing of statement, undated
        - Digest of appellate action on cases, undated, (2 folders) (Box 51)
        - Liddy, G. Gordon, 1973, 1981-1982, undated
        - McCord v. Bailey, 1977-1982
        - Memoranda, opinions, and orders, 1972-1976, (2 folders)
        - Miscellaneous, 1975-1977, undated
        - Notes, undated
        - Press
          - 1972-1973, (2 folders)
          - 1974-1984, undated, (2 folders) (Box 52)
        - Sealed documents, 1979-1981
        - Sentences
          - Dean, John W., III, 1973-1974, (2 folders)
          - Kalmbach, Herbert W., 1974
          - LaRue, Fred C., 1973-1975
          - Magruder, Jeb Stuart, 1973-1974, 1982
          - Orders amending judgment and commitments, 1975-1977
        - Tenth anniversary, 1982
        - Ulasewicz, Anthony T., 1983-1984
        - United States Senate (Box 53)
          - Committee on Appropriations, Central Intelligence hearings, 1973
          - Committee on Armed Services, Central Intelligence hearings, 1973, (3 folders)
        - Watergate Special Prosecution Force report, 1974
        - West Publishing Co., 1975-1978
    - Other cases (Box 54)
      - 1199DC, Nat'l Union of Hosp. & Health Care Employees v. National Union of Hosp. & Health Care Employees, 1975
      - Aetna Casualty & Sur. Co. v. Walter, 1967
      - Airline Pilots Ass'n v. National Mediation Bd., 1963
      - Almay, Inc. v. Weinberger, 1976
      - American Pub. Gas Ass'n v. Federal Energy Admin., 1976
      - In re Ampicillin Antitrust Litigation, 1972 For additional material see Container 19, Bench Books
      - Associated Third Class Mail Users v. United States Postal Serv., 1975
      - Attorney Gen. of the United States v. Covington & Burling, 1976
      - Bache Halsey Stuart, Inc. v. French, 1977
      - Baez v. Central Intelligence Agency, 1979
      - In re estate of Ballard, 1958
      - Bamberger v. Clark, 1968
      - Bandlow v. Fenton, 1959
      - Barr v. District of Columbia, 1962
      - Beckwith v. Hampton, 1977
      - Benson v. United States, 1959
      - Big Mama Rag, Inc. v. United States, 1980
      - Black v. Sheraton Corp. of Am., 1969-1971
      - Black v. United States, 1963-1965
      - Blaustein v. Connecticut Gen. Life Ins. Co., 1962
      - Boraks v. Wilson, 1974
      - Bosch v. Rogers, 1959
      - Brantley v. Metropolitan Life Ins. Co., 1957
      - Brinco Mining, Ltd. v. Federal Ins. Co., 1982
      - Britt v. Internal Revenue Serv., 1982
      - Brown v. Califano, 1977
      - Brown v. Califano, 1978
      - Brown v. District Unemployment Compensation Bd., 1975
      - Brown v. Weinberger, 1976
      - Bruce v. United States, 1966
      - Carr v. District of Columbia, 1970
      - Cheung v. Attorney Gen. of the United States, 1975
      - Cokas v. Perkins, 1966
      - Cutler v. Kennedy, 1979
      - Dendy v. Washington Hosp. Center, 1977
      - District of Columbia v. Landmark Servs., 1976
      - District of Columbia v. Moxley, 1979
      - District of Columbia Fed'n of Civic Ass'ns v. Volpe, 1970-1976, undated, (2 folders)
      - District of Columbia Redevelopment Land Agency v. 40 Parcels of Land, Squares 325, 326, 351, & 352, 1959
      - Doe v. Mathews, 1976
      - Douglas Aircraft Co. v. Weeks, 1959
      - East Tenn. Research Corp. v. Tennessee Valley Auth., 1976
      - Edwards v. United States, 1964
      - Electrical equipment litigation (Box 55)
        - Card index
        - Cases (Box 56)
          - City of Burlington v. Westinghouse Elec. Corp.
            - Background information, undated
            - Bench book, 1964-1965
            - Briefs, 1964, (2 folders)
            - Evidence
              - Conspiracy, 1964